[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-
radio.net se radio is brought to you by
the it computer society and by It
software Magazine online at computer.org
software welcome to software engineering
radio and I'm your host javanas proni
and today we'll be discussing green and
sustainable software with two guests
coral cero and felis Garcia Coral is a
full professor at the University of
Castilla lancha and she's a member of
the laros research group where she leads
the research on green and sustainable
software she's the author and editor of
several books among them she edited the
Green in software engineering and
sustainable software both published by
Springer Felix is a full professor in
the department of information
Technologies and systems at the
University of Castilla lancha and he's a
member of the laros research group and
his research interests include business
and software process management software
measurement agile methods and of course
software sustainability coral and Felix
welcome to software engineering radio is
there anything a miss that you'd like to
add I think it's okay from now let's see
at the
end thanks for your kind introduction
it's a pleasure for us to be here today
ah it's pleasure for us as well so let's
get started then what is green software
about and why should we care so
basically it's about defining the
relationship between software and EnV
enironment thus we can talk about green
by in which software is used for
environmental purposes for example an
application to optimize the temperature
of our house or green in in which the
aim is to make software itself GM for
example to use a programming language
that produces energy efficient
applications no doubt it's very
important to use software that helps on
environmental objectives but it is
fundamental to work on making the
software grien because there are a
studies that estimates that by 2030
information technologies will will
require the 20% of global energy
consumption so of course it is more than
software because it includes also
Hardware by they both will be
responsible of this huge necessity of
energy while there are a lot of
initiatives on green on green Hardware
the work on green software are just
beginning maybe because it seems that
software is something ethereal or
something similar but we must be aware
that every software is execute in a
hardware so the way the software has
been built will determine how much
energy it will require to run luckily
there is more than one way to develop a
software application and the green
software aims to ensure that the one
chosen is the one that obtains the least
energy consuming product let's introduce
a bit of terminology because you know
when we talk about green software the
terminology can really be confusing I
read well I found that as sustainable
software Greening software green bind
software I think you mention Coral the
Green in and green by maybe we can
repeat that as well but then there is
also green software engineering software
green ability green it so can you give
us at least Define the main terms and
help us understand them a bit yes
consider that sometimes is also
confusing for us because there is a lot
of terminology there is some confusion
on the terminology also is normal
because the topic is relatively new and
there is even no consensus on the
fundamental concepts let's start for the
higher level concept that is so
sustainability if we use the definition
of sustainable development given by
United Nations brand report which is
meet the needs of the present without
compromising the ability of future
generations to satisfy their own needs
so in this sense software sustainability
is related on how software can be
developed while taking into
consideration environmental social and
economic Dimensions so as to meet the
needs of the present without
compromising the future so this is the
general concept so in this high level we
are talking on more than just the energy
consumption which is usually the the
focus we developed as a matter of fact
the last year I study to determine what
software sustainability is arriving to
the conclusion that there are two
different perspectives on the
convergence between software and
sustainability the first which is about
making software itself sustainable can
be named software sustainability and its
goal is to achieve what we can term as
sustainability in sofware in this
approach sofware sustainability has
three dimension that correspond to the
ones of sustainability human
economic and environmental or also known
green s the green Dimension has been
traditionally the most explored but we
cannot forget the importance to take
care of the other dimensions for
instance in the human Dimension an
action would be to support inclusiveness
ensuring that our software does not
discriminate uses because race of
culture for example preventing the use
or filter by race in dating apps or raal
or gender algorithm is bias in Social
Network work so we have where software
also can have an impact on that for
example on human and economic Dimension
and coming back to the second
perspective we call this software as
part of sustainability and it considers
software as a new dimension of
sustainability including the interaction
of software with the other dimensions of
sustainability in this case even we can
find different proposal from four to
seven dimensions in all the cases the
definition includes the three dimensions
of sustainability human economic
environmental but depending on the study
others are added of course more details
about this can be found in now in one of
our works named software sustainability
and United Nations sustainable
development goals software
sustainability has in any of the two
menion approaches one dimension devoted
to Green sofware we have already
explained the difference between green
in and green by software which is the
other way to approach this this concept
and of course we can also find the
corresponding concepts related with
Hardware s as Greening Hardware an
example of this is to design for example
a processor more energy efficient or
green by hardware for example to build a
device that controls the water flow of a
garden to optimize its use so both
software and Hardware make up the
Information Technology field also we can
find there green in information
technology and green by information
technology and when we talk about the
green software engineering is in this
Cas is how we approach software
engineering keeping consideration green
exactly well green requirements if we
can call them this way so keeping the
software green somehow or let consuming
fewer resources or there are other
aspects in that how to apply all the
life cycle steps considering the green
aspects of the final product so we are
talking not so only the final product
the greenness of the final product but
also the greenness of how we produce the
product so I don't know the energy
consumed to run the CI bills yeah not
only this but for example the
methodology that we use for the
development or the programming language
or these kind of things so is not only
to take care on the consumption that the
final product will have but also how
this product has been developed during
all this the life cycle phases okay but
but the how also has an impact on the
environment the how for example in
highly automated environments do we have
an estimate on how much energy we could
save with using software engineering
principles are there any estimates out
there we cannot say this final figure
just for software because all the
numbers that we have is is related to
Information Technology as a whole okay
and the problem also when we talk about
green software is that we don't have
just a kind of software or so it's very
difficult to generalize to try to have
this final number so depending on what
we focus the software engineering
principles and the practices to save
energy we need to adapt what we want
okay so I'm going to to explain you a
couple of examples that we have related
to this and the fact that really to do
the things in a given manner impact on
the final consumption of the product
resulting okay so the first case I'm
going to to explain is about data
compression algorithms is related with
one of the big problems we have now with
the software is the data okay so data
compression the algorithms has a
objective to compress the data the
collection of data in order to have to
save space okay so you can have the same
data but with less space we have worked
with the people from launa here in Spain
because they Define algorithms for
compressing data but with the
particularity that you can use this data
in its compressed form so it's not
necessary to decompress the data to use
them okay of course course this implies
Savings in size and also in time to
access the data but what we wanted to
know is to evaluate if the difference of
energy efficient of the energy needed to
access the compressed data were similar
to The Savings in time okay compared
with the collection not compressive so
we evaluated the difference needed to
search on an original text and
compressed and in the same text but
compressed using one of their algorithms
called and Target Den code okay so what
we did was to to search to do searches
on both Collections and as a result we
found that of course the consumption was
lower when the text was compressed this
is logical we have less data to access
so the consumption is lesser but the
important thing is that meing the size
savings when the compressing data was
around a 30% the Energy savings arrived
until the 50% of energy okay so the
percentage of savings in consumption are
greater than the Savings in desserts in
the size and this is very important
because it's a way to explain people
that it's good to find how to manage the
data and maybe the data compression
algorithms can be a solution because
there are a lot of savings of
consumption having the same
functionality of course that's
interesting because it's also really you
say on consumption but also you save on
time as well so well on space at least
so that is a kind of that is an
incentive somehow to use that outside
being Greener yeah of course you are
saving space you are saving time you are
saving energy all these are Savings in
money this is clear and you are not
losing functionality which is very
important also because you can do
exactly the same that you do with the
uncompressed data so these kind of
recommendations are the one that we want
to explain the people that there are
other ways to do the same things but
taking into account this the consumption
I can also present you another example
this time is with a spring spring is a
server side Java development framework
the thing of spring is that it reduces
the time to Market of new applications
helps developers to save a great deal of
development time and improves the
productivity of the of the developers at
least they say that this this is why is
spring is very very used so the study we
did our objective was to discover
whether all the advantages of spring
were also accompied by good energy
consumption Behavior so we have
developed three different applications
the same applications with the same
functionality in both cases developed
with Java but in one case we used also
spring and in another no we Ed just Java
so from the point of view of the
execution time it seems to be better to
avoid the use of a spring okay so the
execution time is worse in the
applications developed by using spring
if we focus on the energy consumption
the use of a spring is not positive
neither for the hard disk and nor for
the computer the whole computer but it's
especially negative from the point of
view of the processor what the
consumption of the spring version is
greater much greater than that of the
non-spring version in all the
applications we developed and this is
very important because this put on the
focus something very important is that
the software industry must take into
account not only the benefit of using
these kind of Frameworks only thinking
on development time of the time to
Market they need to also consider the
negative aspects for example in this
case the the consumption of the final
solution and of course for the people
that develop the this kind of Frameworks
it's mandatory to make make them aware
that they need to work on these
platforms and consider for example green
aspects when they evolve in their
products so there are a lot of lines of
work yeah that's interesting that's
interesting definitely interesting
because bring you know and other
Frameworks maybe similar ones are widely
used in the industry but people don't
necessarily realize what the other the
side effects of doing that thank you for
that is I think our listeners will be
really interested in knowing
this maybe they don't like this
but I'm sure there could be some people
that like spring and they are B beit
disappointed and some others that don't
like and say I Told You So developers
you know how programmers how we are
yeah what are the metrics that or
standards that are commonly used in the
industry to measure the impact of
software from a green perspective are
there any for us this is the critical
point you know one of the basic
principles in software quality and
measurement is that we cannot control
and therefore we cannot improve what we
cannot measure so this is for us key so
if we look at the market we can find
approaches to sare energy consumption
measurement which are mainly of two
types Hardware based is to say using
Hardware measuring instrument like for
example a power meter of course with
this you can provide more accurate and
realistic conception measurements but
you have other possibility as which is
to use estimation models mainly
supported by software tools so of course
these last are more accessible for user
who intend to conduct energy evaluation
of software but in the counterpart they
provide a less reliable and accurate
results on of energy consumption as
compared with the hardware devices one
wellknown sofware tool for this for
estimation is rapel which takes
advantage of the capabilities of modern
Intel processors to estimate their
energy consumption and to obtain
different values about the overall
consumption the different course the
memory included also in the processors
so you can obtain a lot of data about
that but it's estimation okay and so I
guess this looks like is we are a bit at
the initial stages of creating these
instruments because I could imagine that
a usefulness would not that much on the
PC but maybe in data centers machines
there and with the ability to maybe
measure not only the processor but also
split by which virtual machine is using
how much and then maybe within the
virtual machine which processes so from
what I hear since that there is a lot of
ground to cover to get there yeah data
center is even other field in the sense
that there are a lot of advances
specific advanage in order for example
to message Data Center and there are
specific metrics for data centers but in
this case even is difficult to isolate
the specific conception of a software
application which is running a data
center so our idea with this kind of
experimental Laboratories is to help
software practitioners also to try to
understand better the specific impact of
the pieces of software they are testing
there okay that's interesting because I
guess these are make kind of exciting
times for researchers on this because
seems to be pretty much at the beginning
yeah yeah in fact another problem is
that usually most of the solutions that
say that they are measuring consumption
they are really estimating so this is a
little bit dangerous because they don't
provide real consumption real
measurements so you are taking decisions
in data that are not as really reliable
as desire and also we have the problem
of the standardization because we don't
have standards of course we don't know
how to measure imagine to have a
standards so maybe the standards the
most similar standards must be the one
of the iso related to software quality
because there is a kind of relationship
between the Energy Efficiency of the
software quality so maybe this standard
can be used in somehow something is not
an standard but is generalized is is the
Blue Angel Blue Angel is an initiative
of the German government is developed by
some researchers but what they want is
to Define an environmental label for
resource and energy efficient software
products and they are working on this
they work also on the process that
includes things like the choice of
Technology the programming languages
databases all these kind of things idea
behind the blue angine is a good idea is
to award this label to software products
that demonstrate to use Hardware
resources in a particular efficient
manner in any case we are not so
convinced about the label because we
think the topics is not mature enough
and there are a lot of things to take
into consideration before be able to
Define this echol label but we think
it's it's a good point of start and
these initiatives are necessary to
advance on the topics we have also the
green software Foundation the green
software Foundation is a nonprofit
organization based on the USA this
Foundation has a objective the creation
of an ecosystem of people standards
tooling best practices to Green software
they have not still proposed standards
but at least they have specific working
group on it so taking into account the
people that is here in this gr software
Foundation they are 58 member
organizations like accentor globant
Microsoft entity data and a lot of
people more so we think they are on the
way to have these standards but maybe we
can use them as a first step as a
industry proposal to use them as basis
for the creation of General standards by
used by the regulatory organization so
we have not the standards we have not a
final model to be used to label software
products but at this they start to be
initiatives and this is very important
okay now you mention we already
mentioned cloud computing data center so
what is the role the data centers and
cloud computing play into you know in
green software engineering yeah this is
a very interesting point which is of
great importance nowadays you know we
the increasing demand of cloud computing
resources so now many business
businesses which are being digitalized
in Cloud need hosting in that centers
and the user of course the users have to
access to these services or to these
business functions by using a large
variety of devices PCS laptops tablets
smartphones so on so the resulting
energy consumption has to be analyzed
from all the perspectives if we go to
the data center site one key Point here
is that obviously if you optimize your
data center you can reduce its carbon
footprint and Cloud Solutions providers
are expected to be I in a suitable
management of their data centers to
achieve this Aim so for many companies
moving to Cloud solutions would imply a
positive impact on the green Dimension
let's for instance think about a company
managing its own data center or moving
it to the cloud so traditional data
center management implies that it must
be planned and implemented the Computing
storage and other resources in an
anticipated way to support the expected
workload demand usually this can involve
providing and deploying more resources
than actual un need which also involves
cost over rants so companies are seeking
to reduce this by moving to the cloud
with models as for instance pay as you
go that is to say you only pay for the
resources you are consuming which of
course you can configure in a
responsible way and then the cloud
providers also can give you the needed
flexibility to satisfy the war log
demand so the results from an
environmental perspective can be
positive as companies are better
tailoring the cloud services to their
needs and on the other side spe
specialized Cloud providers can manage
their data centers from energy impact
Viewpoint so even some solutions offered
by providers use artificial intelligent
algorithms for example to do vertical
and orizontal scaling depending on the
real time application demand so as a
result they needed visual machines
containers databases and storage are
always appropriately sized to this
demand so this providers have the
specific knowledge the specialized
knowledge needed perhaps to obtain also
great improvements in energy and of
course also there are some efforts now
to reduce the impact of cloud providers
for example Amazon or Microsoft are part
of the climate pled a commitment to
reach Net Zero carbon emissions by 2014
another relevant example of course is
Google which has the Google
sustainability initiative among others
for pursuing net Z emissions across the
Google operations and value Chain by 203
so in this sense Google plans to operate
their data centers and office campuses
on 247 carbon free energy for example by
using solar and wind energy moreover
Amazon web services cloud has an
emissions calculator that allows its
customers to see their impact on what
they outlo and use of Amon Cloud
infrastructure and other providers of
course also offer similar Solutions but
let me please Javan to put I'm now the
bad cop because
yeah Felix has told about all the good
things this is the Happy view
now but it's not as ideal situation
because despite all the advantages of
data centers that felis has already
mentioned and all the efforts to reduce
the electric electricity needs and the
serero emissions and the alternative
energy sources and all these things
there is an estimation that quantifies
the electric usage in data centers grow
in 2030 to almost 3 th000 terab hours
three times more than right now this
year okay so seven years three more
times or energy requirements for the
data centers so we have a problem and
it's because there is a a digitalized
magazine that claims that we can cut
huge amount of of emissions but mve into
digital but all those digitized Services
still require electricity to run they
can be greener but what about all those
data centers that are not worry about
their consumption because there are a
lot of data centers that they don't
thinking on alternative energy sources
and all these kind of things and here we
have a problem we need to make people
aware of this people of the data centers
okay I want to remember the data that we
gave before that in 2025 every day
463 exabytes of data will be created
daily and of course all these data must
be stored and managed and these go
mainly to the these data centers so we
have a real problem with the consumption
so we need to take this into
consideration and then when deciding for
local Cloud solution to consider also
the consumption derived of the network
traffic if they have good uh solutions
for the energy consumption and all these
kind of things because with data we have
a problem despite all the positive
things that we have mentioned so a
question now since we are introducing we
are talking about so companies maybe
that care about power consumptions so
for example the I can imagine Microsoft
Google and these companies Amazon caring
a lot because basically that is also
business I mean the less they consume
the more money they make to provide the
same services so they have a big
incentive to actually act on that yeah
so I think in the news we often read
Google or Amazon putting data centers in
places where they have access to Greener
energy or use less of it because the
place is really cold so they can
actually cool down the data centers
using less power and things like this
but then you know for other companies
let's say they use these data centers
yeah what would be the advantages of
investing in green software for them
because I think this is a crucial point
it's like if they have to spend money to
make the software Greener I don't see
any incentive there to actually go green
yeah so what could be good incentives
for that yeah many times also we
discover that companies are Greener
because they are trying to save money
and when they save money as a result
also the solution is greener so this is
a typical scenario also and what about
the other side no is okay I try to be
green and as a result I will try to save
money also because I have to invest but
also I can perhaps do a better use of
resources more efficiently and as a
result can find some incentives to do
that for example we can find the number
of clear advantages for software
companies to invest in green software
the first is that if they make their
processes green they will directly
obtain Savings in their energy
consumption so in addition if they
develop energy efficient sofware
products and solutions they will be
positioning themselves against
competitors offering their users
something different and this different
will go hand in hand with an aspect of
great concern to society which is to
protect the environment so at the end
also companies need to move towards
obtaining Greener Solutions and
sometimes also they can be obtained by
opting for for cl solution sometimes is
related if I move to Cloud perhaps I
also obtain some advantages in order to
create a Greener products as a result so
this also connect with a third Advantage
which has to do with the company
reputation so it's clear that with the
sensitivity that exists today with the
environment promoting environmentally
friendly products and services make the
brand green and increase the reputation
so there are many reasons for example
for a company to be greener and of
course in the how and also in the what
in the re in the service of prod results
and evidently this contribution ofare
May imply an increase in production cost
which probably be reflected in the final
price of the product or service as a
consequence however we are convinced
that this is a profitable investment if
you go for green you are making a good
investment why for example let's
consider when a user goes to buy a
refrigerator in addition to the
functionalities and the price many times
we look the information about energy
efficiency of the refrigerator and also
because it's affecting to our consume
conception as user so my final decision
to buy the refrigerator in not only the
the cost or the price I consider other
variables and I try to obtain or to I
seek a balance between all the
information provided to take the
decision so this echol level is an
important part also of my decision so we
should also advance in this sense in for
software products because this will also
help companies to invest in a stronger
way in order to be greener in the in the
solution okay so in a way this is also a
contribution that users can give it's
like they know that some software
solution that solves their problem is
greener than an equivalent one that
might become parameter in the choice is
the example in the fridge let's say that
you are asked to give some advice to
software developers and development
organization that want to look to
prioritize sustainability in the
software practices how should they get
started with that we have to start from
requirements from the licitation of the
requirements so there we have to include
our specific requirements related with
for example power consumption or energy
consumption so as much as possible and
generally speaking all the software like
cycle states must incorporate decision
driven by these green requirements for
instance choosing the best combination
of compiler programming language to
fulfill these green requirements
adopting suitable software architecture
we think into account these green
aspects or applying the Green Design
patterns or apply green refactoring or
optimize my code considering also the
impact on energy of course and these are
only a few examples but the most
important thing is to be aware that
green requirement or more in general
even sustainable requirements must be
also fulfilled and decisions must be
also in accordance with it we have to
take decisions in accordance with the
requirements of course this also
requires a suitable infrastructure and
tools in order to help developers to
make make better decisions and be
informed about their impact as Engineers
also we have to measure and as we
mentioned earlier the engineers has to
be aware of the impact of their
decisions so they need data they need
data about the energy so they can try
they can test their Solutions in order
to build Greener ones and in this case
also perhaps in in our opinion it can be
interesting to follow kaen principles
like in process Improvement is I try to
do a small change I evaluate it and I
see if there are improvements in energy
so I don't have clear guidelines to do
that perhaps I can find something I can
check I can try measure and then improve
so we are starting also with that and
then in the resarch community there are
a lot of studies in which is to provide
developers with s guidelines or I'll for
example mention some studies also for
example if we talk about design patterns
there are some studies which demonstrate
we design pattern can be better from
energy point of view than other
or B smells in the code that can also
affect to the energy consumption for
example duplicated code duplicated code
sometimes involves also impact on energy
so developers we can provide developer
with this kind of guidelines but there
are a lot of things also and lot of
knowledge to discover is it yeah I think
I have another comment here that it's
very important to have the developers
involved on this green software but if
we want to have Real Results we need
that the developers are comined by the
company I mean green must be part of the
business processes and the companies
must to bet for them and like this they
will provide the developers with these
tools that Felix mentioned and the
specific measures for the software they
develop so it's a whole we need everyone
involved on this we need all the people
that can have a responsibility into the
software development to be aware and to
want to go for the green software okay
there are some Felix mention all you
know engineer Ing and we need to measure
this but is there a way that for example
we can use something today I don't know
we mentioned before estimating
consumption somehow I think that in the
green software Foundation there is also
a formula for to kind of estimate the
carbon impact that is based on numbers
that usually can be taken from somewhere
I mean is an still an estimate so there
is no Precision there but would be that
a good starting point because I'm asking
this because I can imagine you know
having a formula that gives me a reason
able estimate and something I can test
my software against would be actually
helpful to me as a software engineer to
at least maybe not have the most green
software ever but at least to do
software that is greener than it used to
be and also have something that I can
actually use in my requirement process
and Engineering Process to as a
reference of course it's better
something than nothing so yes there are
not only in the green software
Foundation there are also some
industries that use these kind of
indicators that are mainly used user on
estimates the problem is that what you
have said this is very very strange
things for me it's difficult to have a
general indicator for the green software
in general is dangerous so it maybe it
can be a good point of start but we need
to go on and of course it cannot be the
only thing we need to measure to have
real measurements because if we want to
improve a software we need to know which
part of this software is the most
consumer in all the code for example and
to re engineer this part and have it
Greener the thinking the requirements is
one of the parts most developed into the
green software topic maybe because the
the intuitive idea to Align Energy
Efficiency with something related to the
quality of the software uh and relating
the Energy Efficiency with functional
requirement of software so in fact one
of the first workshops that arose on
this topic was exactly precisely about
sustainable requirements for software
into the requirements engineering
conference so this is a data so it's
possible to find in the literature a lot
of approaches to classify and relate
quality and G measures Define cataloges
of sustainab requirements interactions
between quality and Energy Efficiency a
lot of works but most of them are very
focused I mean some of them are General
but in the sense of analysis but not as
a a catalog of General software
sustainable requirements and we need to
work on this even the concept of
ecological depth has been defined based
on the technical depth but related to
the energy consumption of software so
yeah there are efforts but I think that
again more in a research step than in a
production step so it's necessary to
systematically eliciting analyzing and
document the green requirements
including the energy consumption as an
equal in the green software process the
software engineering process I think we
are on the path we will AR right but
every industry need to work on their own
requirements and the cataloges of
sustainability requirements okay so what
I'm understanding is there isn't really
a good way yet to measure that at least
a way that is precise we have some ways
of estimating this they are not very
precise but maybe even if we start from
there at least we start somewhere we can
start improving the situation so I guess
at least you have an indication that you
are going the right direction the real
is that we don't know how much we are
going into that direction at the end
because it's an estimate there is no
Precision then as you say Coral you
cannot really have one measure for
everything because of the complexity of
of the field so there is a lot of work
to do but we can start doing something
at least yeah I think it's good to start
estimating at least as a first point of
start and to know your systems and to
weigh of work where are your weak points
in the development and in the
consumption you don't have the real real
information but at least you have some
indications and if you want to use some
kind of indicator maybe it's good to try
to adapt to your reality because these
General indicators for me a little bit
dangerous but yes you can use it if you
don't have another thing just to have a
first impression on how you are where
you are and from there trying to go to
advance of the on the way I think that
is really important to know that there
is something we can do now and start
doing at least it's not going to be
perfect it's not going to give us
accurate information but at least will
give us a trend if you're improving or
not and then since we are talking about
engineering and code quality and all
this stuff now a question that for me is
actually quite an interesting one that
is researching for around green software
and sustainability so I found out that
some software design architecture
development practices that are good in
general you know for code quality
somehow of for systems operability are
good for green ability you know things
like caching data close to users good
for both delete unused resources yeah so
instead of leaving cues and things
hanging around clean it up is not only
save money from your cloud provider but
also you'll save energy all these kind
of things that seem to be kind of
obvious but then reading some studies
some good practices seems to be at odd
with green ability and this is where the
engineering B start to become
interesting so for example redundancy of
systems to improve availability yeah so
it's basically a bit over over
provisioning so the system does not go
down and is more available but then
consumes a lot more energy or a coding
level good code practices like
modularizing a god class so God class a
class that does a lot of stuff too much
I found one one study in I think in one
of the books I think in the green
software engineering book an article in
green software maintenance when they run
an experience said let's see if having
this Gold Class thing we refactor it
into a proper modular code that is much
better from maintainability what happens
from a power consumption point of view
and they said oh gosh now he is
consuming much more energy so these are
the aspects that I find interesting
because it's where the engineering
decisions need to be made and I found
also in other books saying well actually
modularity is good because on the
process side will make it easier to
maintain code and make changes so
somehow consuming fewer resources from
another angle so what should we make of
it what a developer on day-to-day work
what should they do yeah yes indeed this
is something that software engineers and
developers have to deal with constantly
you know even not considering energy in
the software quality field sometimes if
we improve usability perhaps you are
decreasing the the security for example
and of course if we now include the
energy in the equation now the situation
the complexity
also increases so this is what we know
as tradeoff at the end when we are
working on software quality and now
considering energy also we have to make
tradeoff decisions this is the point and
what we have to do is to try to analyze
this interactions that can arise have
the different requirements for example
as a matter of fact some years ago we
conducted a literature study about
possible interactions between software
quality characteristics and
sustainability this in this context we
must understand interaction as a type of
dependence between two or more
requirements that have to be satisfied
simultaneously simultaneously in a
software product as for instance for
example I have to fulfill security and
usability and as I commented before
perhaps if I have to promote one getting
worse in the other one of course green
ability should be also part of it and in
our study this we analyze these
interactions between quality and
sustainability for example we analyze
two Dimensions the how and the what so
the process process and the product for
example from process perspective many
research studies take the process
perspective only considering the effects
or backs fixing for example in the sense
if I eliminate more backs in my my
software perhaps the quality of my
process is better so if we also
extrapolate this to energy consumption
this studies report that the correction
of major backs usually lead to lower
power consumption what is logical and
but also is common that energy related
code chains tend to be larger than fish
in a back for example if I try to change
my code in order to turn into Greener
perhap my effort is higher as compared
for example the typical process of
defects or back fixing because energy
effect can affect to not only a a
specific module for example in which I
discover the back but energy is spread
across different software models the
impact on energy can be explained by the
fact that ever a set of models which are
interacting are affecting to this energy
and from product quality perspective for
example we also analyze this possible
interaction for example let's compare
functionality and energy it's expected
that functionality of application is
directly proportional to energy
consumption in the sense more functions
as oftware product provides more
conception so other example is privacy
privacy perhaps will have a negative
influence on sustainability because I
have to add more components privacy
component more in order to support
usually these privacy requirements so as
a result perhaps wors in the energy so
at the end this is an example of
tradeoff I have my application has to
fulfill this privacy but how much
privacy in the sense that the needed
privacy in order also for for example to
be greener so this is a trade of
decision I have to find good balance
between for example the Privacy my
system has to have with regards to the
the energy consumption as as consequence
so there are a lot of examples in this
sense for example as you mentioned Joan
refactoring refactoring is not always
good from energy Viewpoint in some
studies some refactoring techniques have
a negative impact on Energy Efficiency
for example simply due to the fact that
if I have to add new methods and new
classes for something I increase as a
result the number of messages between
objects and as a result my system is
consuming more but only applying
refactoring so what we can do provide
guidelines and to help to made this
trade of decisions in the best way in
the sense that okay take care take care
if you apply the refactoring technique
take care about the number of messages
or take care about the number of new
classes you are included in your system
so at the end this is the point we have
to find a right balance so what this
would also is that in community research
and even practitioner Community yes
there are some refactoring techniques
and some mechanisms are being pro to be
useful for example memorization with
what we commented about the c or to
store the results of Highly
computational functions so instead of
calling a function which is very heavy
very energy demanding several times
perhaps I include the results in a c and
when I have to go back to this function
perhaps I can retrieve the result from
the C and avoid unnecessary calls to
this heavy energy functions so we can
find what is good of this is that we can
find good mechanisms and we can evaluate
the and at the end as engineers and as I
told before I could make the best
decision but the tradeoff is present
always this looks like some of the work
that I saw in the green software
foundation with the patterns page
basically evaluating some ways of doing
things that are considered good ways but
then attaching the green warnings about
the cost to me looks like that we have
to somehow reevaluate the good practices
or what they are considered good
software engineering practices in the
eye of green ability and green software
and sustainability I guess you know in a
way that is perhaps similar also to I
don't know security security we know a
lot about what is good or bad because
it's been the focus of a lot of research
and lots of grief also for many
companies and I guess we need to do
something similar in the Green Space
exactly this is the point we need more
research and we need more practice in
Industry to have these guidelines
General guidelines that can be used by
anyone who develop software and use this
kind of Technology of course at the end
if you have these guidelines these good
practices green good practices then you
can make your decisions when you are the
developing and this is the point we are
not there but we are going because yeah
but there are I've seen already some
recommendations not for everything but
we are starting again yes it seems to be
a very young field at the moment even if
it's been around for a few years but
probably not with a strong Focus that
you have now yeah but you know also
because we had not the devices to
measure nor the estimators so in a lot
of years of the topic have been just for
defining the things and to understand
the things and now we have the
estimators and some devices to measure
and this is a point of inflection let's
say I think in our studies we try always
to as a result to provide this kind of
guidelines to generate these guidelines
to later be used in the software
industry because if we are measuring
having conclusions is also to have
lessons learn and this lessons learn and
this guidelines we think we can give
something important and interesting to
the software Community okay now my next
question is something I must ask because
it's a part of a programmer's favorite
if you like so about programming
languages are there languages that are
better than others for green software
before going to the answer do you have
any idea of which language can be the
worst
or surely not the ones I
use okay maybe Felix can explain some I
hope we will have no new haters after
our answers to this to this question
because now there are studies about that
but yes fortunately which is very good
for programmers is that they have choose
among a wide variety of programming
languages to meet their objectives
sometimes the programming language to be
used perhaps is a constraint of the
project perhaps is imposed by the
company or by the client but many other
times you can choose and the choice of
one language or another can affect also
the green aspect and what are the
criteria there are a lot for example we
can distinguish between Technical and
non-technical factors in order to choose
a programming language such as the
exraction level is important level
because as we will discover usually the
best languages are low struction level
so at the end for program is not easy to
apply them for productivity for example
so a struction level project domain for
example if you are programming the front
end the back end or your proes of data
science so another factors of course are
related with the learning cve the system
documentation of the language the
supporting libraries including the
language for your purpose and even a lot
of factors so this choice of a suitable
programming language or a set of them
because you know some projects are not
composed only of components of
implementing in only one programming
language is an important decisions that
can impact productivity quality and of
course the green Dimension so if we
focus on the green dimensions in the
same way programmers are choosing a
language for performance requirements
these energy conception requirements
should be also included in the selection
criteria so this is important again
awareness so when I have to choose a
language let's consider also the energy
impact so of course on our side what is
our work to provide programmers with
studies in different scenarios of
application so they can make the
decision supported by evidence and so we
got any languages you can mention yes
yeah in fact there is a complete study
did by people from Portugal they have
made they analyze the energy consumption
of 27 programming languages of
algorithms that they took from a
benchmark so with the results of the
consumption they elaborated a ranking
okay and before the results just to give
some more emotion they used an estimator
I think they use rap l for the results
so in the top the best programming
languages are C C++ and Java and bascal
these are the more respectful on the
other part the languages with higher
consumption are Ruby Python and pearl so
in general the interpreted languages are
more consumer than the compiled in
general okay so we have another
interesting result of this study is that
not always the fastest solution is the
most energy efficient so the energy
consumption is not related with time
this is very important because usually
people think okay less time less
consumption and this is not always true
okay in this case for example is not so
we have replicated this study the people
from Portugal but using our measurement
device and we have the same
classification more or less different
values for the consumption but the same
for the ranking let's say there is
another aspect to that we must take into
consider
and is the compiler the use of compilers
and interpreters okay so these are the
results this means that the people that
uses python need to change to another
programming language so maybe it is not
the solution but maybe they can start to
change and try to know if they have very
high computational problems to solve
maybe they can move to other programming
language okay so it's not to close the
industry and to start from now from
scratch everything but to evolve to
another programming language is also
fair to say that I know that for example
python is used a lot in data analysis in
AI but also python has a very good
interface with C so there are plenty of
libraries that are actually very
efficient in Python because they're
written in C and they are used very
easily from python so is one of those
situations where actually the context
matters yeah so you can write lots of
your code in Python yeah but and the
computational Intensive bits are done by
native librar so at the end of the day
in practice your code might be actually
quite green yeah in the sense that the
bits that you've written in Python don't
have such a big impact overall yeah so I
think that is interesting to know this
thing about the languages but it's also
interesting important to know that is a
the test is a specific context so some
algorithms written in the language and
the context of use in different projects
may be different and so is important to
to know that so people can make inform
judgment in fact in our experiments we
noticed that for example there was not
the same Energy Efficiency of the
programming language on all the
algorithms we tested so perhaps in one
algorith programming language was better
than other from an energy point of view
so at the end is very important to
consider the context and of course also
it's not only just about the programming
language you have also to consider the
compiler or interpreter as Coral also
mentioned because sometimes I need
python because for example I'm not an
expert in C or in C++ and for
productivity in my project I I'm using
python because I have the libraries I
need to fulfill my requirements so at
the end what I can do perhaps python in
our results only the results from the
study of Portugal and our study is one
of the worst so at the end perhaps okay
I need python what can I do let's choose
good compiler in order to mitigate this
effect on energy so this at the end is a
combination programming language with
effective compilers in order also
to Solutions yes contest environment and
so on and also I like to remark one of
the points mentioned by K time because
in thearch community is very useful for
us because for example when we analyze
studies from 10 years ago or more than
that in which they mention green
sometimes they mention green but at the
end they are not measuring the energy
because they only mention okay my
solution is faster in time so it's
Greener so at the end of course many
solutions which are faster in time are
Greener because in the equation we have
energy consumtion is equal to time
multiplied by the energy of course yes
time is important in the equation but
this not only the only variable and
there are a lot of other studies
especially in concurrency systems in
which in short time perhaps you are
doing a very intensive usage of
resources which at the end is producing
a um more energy more energy than slower
programs yeah so you can basically be
saving energy by going parallel
consuming a lot but for a short time so
the time saved is so much that actually
that overall energy is less I guess that
is the kind of one of those rules where
if I'm faster I'm Greener is kind of a
lot of time is correct but not all that
all of the time and people make the
mistake of considering it correct always
yeah because if not we have the solution
it's just a matter of time
true true wouldn't be so difficult just
make now I want to ask something big
that is obviously mandatory in our days
and I know that you have something to
say about it is about AI yeah the impact
of AI on green software and
sustainability at the beginning you
mention a bit about that so the fact
that AI is actually a large consumer of
energy let's see so we know that can
consume a lot so we can talk a bit about
this but also I'm particularly
interested in knowing how we can use AI
to actually overall reduce the consume
of energy if it is possible yeah this is
a good point because artificial
intelligence can be used to help to
reduce the consumption of any aspect so
in that case we are talking about
getting by AI okay but we have also the
gree in AI is how to program and how to
work with the artificial intelligent
algorithms in order to make a good
solutions from the Energy Efficiency
point of view so these are two
perspectives very important the thing is
that there are a lot of efforts in green
by artificial intelligence because it's
a good solution of course it's a very
computational solution to solve problems
to manage a lot of data and have this
kind of learn knowledge but we cannot
make the artificial intelligence the
problem if we want to use it a solution
we must to be sure that artificial
intelligence is not contributing to the
problem so that's why it's important to
work on the Green in artificial
intelligence there is a study which
estimate that training computers to
learn human speech generates five times
the level of CO2 emissions of an average
car during its entire lifetime one
training algorithm five lives of a car
just one algorithm is just the training
so we have a problem here and the thing
is that again we go to the tradeoff we
are asking the artificial intelligence
to solve almost of our problems today
they are able to manage a lot of data
and they can go to good solutions for a
lot of problems more or less important
so the artificial intelligence Community
is to solve the problems but they are
not aware of the consequences on how
they are doing it because they are
trying to maximize the accuracy for
example to maximize the accuracy means
to increase a lot of the computation and
to increase the computation means more
Energy Efficiency so if I am
recommending a film to watch on Netflix
maybe it's not important to have a
Precision of the 99% on the
recommendation so just to go down two or
three points on this recommendation May
save three times of energy consumption
okay of course if I'm trying to help the
doctors in the health system in that
case I need to be very accurate because
the result is important to be applied
okay so here is where we need to play
with this balance between the accuracy
and the amount of resources that I put
on the algorithm of artificial
intelligence to give the solution that
way is how we can avoid to make the
artificial intelligent to also be a
problem okay and then now another thing
that I think is important I mean what
are educational institutions and maybe
also the industry if you know what are
doing to actually educate software
Engineers on green software green
software engineering and all these
aspects is there anything happening in
that respect unfortunately for the
moment we don't noce special efforts in
Academy right now to incorporate these
skills of course one part this is normal
because you know as we have been talking
now sustainable sofware is a field
relatively new with many challenges to
to face so for for instance it's more
difficult now in in careers or in
academic profiles to introduce green
software design or coding in the
curricula if there are not the required
guidelines we don't have the required
supporting tools and so on so it's more
difficult but of course we have to start
to promote this also so it's positive
for example that sustainability is being
Incorporated more explicitly in relevant
bodies of knowledge for example
Computing curricular for instance the
ACM software engineering curricular
version of 2014 only mention
sustainability as a general outcome but
it is not included explicitly but for
example if we look now at the current
beta version of 2023 of computer science
curricula sustainability is proposed to
be part of a knowledge area which is
named Society ethics and
professionalisms so what we can expect
here is that perhaps the curricular also
for sare engineers will give this
importance to sustainability in the next
update so we notice certain movement in
this direction which is good and how to
incorporate this knowledge in our
curricula in our opinion we have at
least to tackle the management and
Technical perspective Management in the
sense that you have to manage your
projects considering sustainability and
for example wellknown bodies of
knowledge like PM book the project
management body of knowledge also
recognize sustainability is an important
part in the in the management of a
project and on the other side from the
technical perspective our opinion is
that perhaps this is not a question of
for example design a new curricula about
about green software the point is for
example to include this green concept or
green techniques tools in the necessary
knowledge areas for example in design if
our students are learning about how to
design to build a software which is more
maintainable in the same sense we have
to educate them to build this software
in a Greener way this is only an example
so at the end is to incorporate these
techniques and these tools when they are
more mature in the curricula in a normal
way not creating new contents or in this
sense or new subject or something like
of course what is needed is the some
subject specific on the fundamentals
this is important also yes and then
guess the last question I have so the
future of greens and sustainable
software perhaps maybe mentioning also
some projects you are involved in what
do you see happening say in the next 5
to 10 years considering the advances now
and the this Movement we are talking
about perhaps we witness that the main
challenge to be address in the the next
years can be the following first of all
standardization so we need for example
we talk about even terminology is not
standardized so we need the standards in
order to create this harmonization and
to join forces in order to advance in
the field so perhaps ISO and i e are
expected to make some word on that in
order to help every people to move
toward sustainable software and
specifically also to Green software the
second one we talk also about that
measurement we mentioned the maturity of
the measurement of for example energy
consumption is relatively low we can say
even perhaps we measure with Hardware
instruments you need a specialized
infrastructure and a specialized
knowledge and of course if we measure
with the measure even you need also
specialized knowledge so at the end we
have to work on that direction in also
to provide developers with easier ways
or for example to automate this for them
to provide the results automatically for
them avoiding them dis effort in the
same way for example a programing
language with higher abstraction layer
abstracts from developer this a lot of
things so perhaps our efforts also
should be in that direction of course
when we advance with the measurement
also we can ADV with Advance with the
guidelines in the sense that more
empirical studies are conducted
practitioners even also can have real
cases of application of different ACS in
order to see if they are Greener or not
so at the end this empirical body of
knowledge is expected also to grow to
grow and it can be us as we also remark
in this talk there are not gold reses or
solution for all but perhaps we can
build this empirical evidence in
different context in order to help in
order to help so we have to also advance
in this sense and finally and not the
least we need the effort of the
governments and efforts from
professional and research communities to
the development of a green certification
and we need Associated legislation for
that so this perhaps is would have a
great impulse for companies especially
in order to be more aware of the
importance of building Green Solutions
and also to help in this sense I think
that little bit more pessimistic than
Felix I think that if we don't have
legislation we have a problem because to
invest in green is to invest money we
have already talked about this and if
the industry don't see the benefit in
the short term I think they will resist
to the change so we need this
legislation and the European Union is
doing efforts in this line also in the
United States are doing things of
related with the missions of the
technology and the software so I think
it's mandatory to have this legislation
and to put the industry to must do the
things it's very important and also
another for me very very important
challenge for now right now is to give
the green and sustainable software its
room educating the people spreading the
world making the people from IND and
Industry aware of this problem and add
the impact of the software to the
discourse we have a problem and we need
to handle okay thank you very much I
hope it doesn't sound too much of a kind
of pessimistic closing I think there is
a lot of optimistic stuff we can think
of you know with the progress he's
making but I agree with you that is
important that government do something
to provide the appropriate Frameworks
and incentives we need to fight against
the Green Wasing and we have a lot of
green Wasing in Industry a lot of green
Wasing yeah that is always the case with
anything I I think yeah well anyway I
think at the end of the interview I
think we have done quite a great job to
introduce green and sustainable software
I hope that our listeners will come out
with something they can do thank you
very much Felix and thank you for coming
to the show has been a real pleasure yes
thank you for invitation thank you very
much
enjoyed we have enjoyed a lot this thank
you so and this is Jaan proni for
software engineering radio thank you for
listening thanks for listening to SC
radio an educational program brought to
you by It software magazine for more
about the podcast including other
episodes visit our website at se-
radio.net to provide feedback you can
comment on each episode on the website
or reach us on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter
or through our slack Channel at seo.
slack.com you can also email us at Team
[Music]
c-rnli under creative comments license
2.5 thanks for
[Music]